Arash Pourhabibi-Zarandi

Member of Technical Staff (IC3), Oracle

CONTACT INFO

ADDRESS: Prime Tower (Floor 17), Hardstrasse 201, 8005 Zurich, Switzerland

EMAIL: arash.pourhabibi@oracle.com WEBSITE: http://arash.pourhabibi.info

INTERESTS

I am broadly interested in the field of computer systems and interdisciplinary systems-level problems found in modern, large-scale datacenters, from cloud services to data stores and all the way down to server systems. By characterizing modern datacenter applications, I look for maximizing the compute density of server systems and minimizing their energy footprint through specialization of various system components and better system integration. In my PhD thesis, I focused on evading of the RPC tax in datacenters through hardware-software co-design.

EDUCATION

2015-2021 Ph.I

Ph.D. in Computer & Communication Sciences

Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne, Switzerland

Doctoral Research Assistant at PARSA under supervision of Prof. Babak FALSAFI

Thesis: Hardware-Software Co-Design of an RPC Processor

Related Courses: Advanced Multiprocessor Architecture, Topics on Datacenter Design, Understanding Datacenter Software

Dynamics

2013-2015

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering (Software Engineering)

Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran

Thesis: Design & Implementation of a Scheme for Big Data Processing on GPU

Advisor: Dr. Farshad Khunjush

Ranked First: Achieving the highest course GPA (19.84/20) among all M.Sc. students

Related Courses: Advanced OS, Advanced Computer Architecture, Multicore Programming, Parallel Algorithms, Grid Comput-

ing, Software Architecture, Text Mining

2009-2013

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering (Software Engineering)

Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran

Ranked First: Achieved the highest GPA in CS courses (18.88/20) among all B.Sc. students

WORK EXPERIENCE

CURRENT | Member of Technical Staff (IC3) | Oracle, Zurich, Switzerland

DEC. 2021 Part of the R&D team working on MySQL Heatwave.

2015-2021 | Doctoral Research Assistant | PARSA, EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

Contributed to several research projects focused on hardware and software co-design for future generations of datacenter servers. Supervised junior students and summer interns. Member of the CloudSuite team, and part of the core team responsible for its 3rd release. Member of the Flexus simulator maintenance team, and part of the core team working on its new incarnation

branded as QFlex.

2010-2013 | Member of the IT Task Force | CS Department, Shiraz University, Iran

In charge of the maintenance of department's network infrastructure and IT services. Proposed and implemented new services

for the department such as a CMS.

2011-2013 | Freelance Java and iOS Developer

Involved in development of a payment switch system (in Java). Co-founded the Mobile Programming group at Shiraz University

and developed a bill payment app for iPhone.

2010-2011 | Intern at Shiraz University's CERT Center (ShirazAPA)

Involved in research and development of several security-related projects such a secure update manager.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: Python, C/C++, Java, PThreads, OpenMP, CUDA, MPI

Operating Systems: macOS, Linux, Windows

Miscellaneous: Git, Docker, LaTeX, Shell Scripting, Agile Development

Basic Familiarity: Objective-C, Ruby, PHP, HTML, JavaScript

PUBLICATIONS & PATENTS

- 1. **Cerebros: Evading the RPC Tax in Datacenters.** A. Pourhabibi, M. Sutherland, A. Daglis, B. Falsafi. *In Proceedings of the 54th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture, MICRO'21*, Athens, Greece, October 2021.
- 2. Equinox: Training (for Free) on a Custom Inference Accelerator. M. Drumond, L. Coulon, A. Pourhabibi, A. Yüzügüler, B. Falsafi, M. Jaggi. *In Proceedings of the 54th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture, MICRO'21*, Athens, Greece, October 2021.
- 3. Data Transformer Apparatus. A. Pourhabibi, S. Gupta, H. Kassir, M. Sutherland, Z. Tian, M. Drumond, B. Falsafi, C. Koch. *Patent (Pending)*, March 2021.
- 4. **Optimus Prime: Accelerating Data Transformation in Servers.** A. Pourhabibi, S. Gupta, H. Kassir, M. Sutherland, Z. Tian, M. Drumond, B. Falsafi, C. Koch. *In Proceedings of the 25th ACM International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems, ASPLOS'20*, Lausanne, Switzerland, March 2020.
- 5. Towards near-threshold server processors. A. Pahlevan, J. Picorel, A. P. Zarandi, D. Rossi, M. Zapater, A. Bartolini, P. G. Del Valle, D. Atienza, L. Benini, and B. Falsafi. *In Proceedings of the 2016 Conference on Design, Automation & Test in Europe (DATE)*, Dresden, Germany, March 2016.
- 6. The official Persian translation of "Engineering SaaS: An Agile Approach Using Cloud Computing" written by Armando Fox and David PATTERSON. *Currently under preparation*.

AWARDS & HONORS

DEC. 2018	Awarded the Teaching Assistant Award for teaching excellence
	School of Computer & Communication Sciences (IC), EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland
SUMMER 2014	Ranked 2 nd at the first Iran Programming Skill Challenge (Java section)
	Held by Sharif University of Technology and Tehran University's Faculty of Entrepreneurship, Iran
SEP. 2013	Honorary admission to the M.Sc. program without university entrance exam
	Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran
June 2013	Awarded as the Best Undergraduate Student in Computer Engineering
3	Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran
_	
FEB. 2012	Nominated for the Best Mobile Application for SAHA (payment app for iPhone)
	The First Iran Mobile Innovation Awards, held by Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran

PROFESSIONAL & EXTRACURRICULAR SERVICES

ASPLOS 2020	Artifact	Evaluation	Committee	Member
-------------	----------	------------	-----------	--------

DEC. 2014 | Co-organizer of an Hour of Code Event

Organized a one-day workshop, participating in the Hour of Code program, for tens of high-school and middle-school students and taught them the basics of computer programming and algorithmic thinking.

2010-2014 | BreakTime In University (BTiU)

BTiU is a three-day annual conference consists of tens of parallel workshops held by a group of university students during the summer at Shiraz University. Hundreds of talented high-schoolers attend this event to learn more about various study majors, practice teamwork, life and social skills, and learn how to be creative and innovative. I had the chance to be a part of the organizing team for five years.

MAY 2012 | Member of Conference Organizing Committee

Internet and technical services assistant at the 16^{th} CSI International Symposiums on Computer Architecture & Digital Systems (CADS 2012) and Artificial Intelligence & Signal Processing (AISP 2012) held at Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran.

LANGUAGES

PERSIAN: Native Proficiency

ENGLISH: Full Professional Proficiency FRENCH: Elementary Proficiency

OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS

2015-2021

CloudSuite

CloudSuite is a benchmark suite of cloud services. The benchmarks are based on real-world software stacks and represent real-world setups. It is one of the early benchmark suites that is representative of modern datacenter services and is included in Google's PerfKit Benchmarker. It has become an industry standard and been used to drive the design of modern datacenter-oriented CPUs, such as Cavium ThunderX. I have been a core member of the team responsible for the maintenance and the third release of CloudSuite, which is a major enhancement over prior releases both in benchmarks and infrastructure.

2016-2021

QFlex

The QFlex project targets quick, accurate, and flexible simulation of multi-node computer systems proceeding along four fronts: QEMU, a popular open-source full-system machine emulator, Flexus, a powerful and flexible simulation framework that enables detailed cycle-accurate simulation, SMARTS, which applies rigorous statistical sampling theory to reduce the simulation time while achieving high accuracy, and NS-3, a popular and flexible network simulation stack. I have been a member of the Flexus maintenance team and the team responsible for its new incarnation branded as QFlex.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

FALL 2019 FALL 2018 FALL 2017 FALL 2016	Introduction to Multiprocessor Architecture Assisted in redesigning the course: constructed a new syllabus and prepared course material including lecture slides, exercises, programming assignments, and exams. Graded assignments and exams. Led weekly lab sessions and guided students.
SPRING 2020 SPRING 2019	System Oriented Programming Assisted in redesigning the course: constructed a new course project and weekly tasks for students. Created a grading and feedback infrastructure for the weekly tasks, graded the final project and led weekly lab sessions. EPFL
SPRING 2018	Systems for Data Science Graded students' assignments, projects and exams, held lab sessions and gave guidance to students for their projects. EPFL
SPRING 2017	Programming II (Using C++) Graded students' programming assignments, projects and exams. Led weekly lab sessions and gave guidance to students. EPFL
SPRING 2014	Grid Computing Graded students' programming assignments and projects. Shiraz University
SPRING 2014	Software Architecture Graded students' programming assignments and projects. Shiraz University
SPRING 2014 SPRING 2013	Database Laboratory Completely redesigned the course from scratch. Constructed the syllabus and prepared the course material. Led weekly lab sessions, gave guidance to students and graded their assignments and projects. Shiraz University
FALL 2013	GPU Programming Prepared and graded students' programming assignments and projects, led weekly lab sessions and gave guidance to students. Shiraz University
SPRING 2013	Design & Implementation of Programming Languages Prepared students' programming assignments and projects. Shiraz University
FALL 2012 FALL 2010	Fundamentals of Computer and Programming Using Python Constructed the syllabus and prepared the course material (programming assignments, labs, and projects). Led weekly lab sessions, gave guidance to students and graded their assignments and projects. Shiraz University
SPRING 2012 SPRING 2011	Principles of Programming Using C Prepared and graded students' programming assignments and projects, led weekly lab sessions and gave guidance to students. Shiraz University
F	

Last Update: December 2021

Prepared and graded students' programming assignments and projects, led weekly lab sessions and gave guidance to

FALL 2011 | Advanced Programming Using Java

students. | Shiraz University